[Music]
i've talked about the benefits of beans
and lentils and chickpeas
but do the benefits remain even when
they're powdered
they're a bunch of bean pastas on the
market now made from bean powder instead
of wheat powder
does it have the same benefits as whole
beans
in terms of blood sugar control yes
no differences in blood sugar responses
were observed between whole beans pureed
beans and powdered beans
this study however failed to show a
benefit they gave people powdered
lentils chickpeas peas
and did not see any cholesterol benefits
for example compared to a potato placebo
now conceivably the powdering process
may have altered the properties of the
fiber
but they were only giving people 100
grams a day which is less than half a
can of beans and previous studies that
have shown significant cholesterol
lowering benefits tended to use more
than that
another bean powder study also found no
cholesterol effect but they were only
giving 15 grams a day that's just like
15 beans a day
if you do a systematic review of all the
randomized controlled regular bean
studies significant benefits were found
more like up around 130 grams a day in
other words at least
one full serving
if you ever get sick of pulse pastas and
beans that are canned and cooked
sprouting is a cheap effective and
simple tool for improving the
nutritional quality of certain legumes
i've fawned over lentil sprouts
previously as one of the healthiest
snacks along with kale chips and nori
sheets
anyone can make lentil sprouts at home
super easy for pennies fresh produce
year round on your windowsill
but any way to boost their nutritional
quality even higher
well as a response to
environmental stresses plants modify
their metabolism and we may be able to
take advantage of that to modify the
composition and activity of plant foods
for example
plants are subjected to free radicals
too which can damage their dna just like
it damages our dna so to reduce excess
free radicals plants can ramp up their
antioxidant defenses which we can then
take advantage of when we eat them so
for instance as a germination technique
for chickpeas if you irradiate them with
gamma rays you can boost their
antioxidant defenses
but if you don't want to bruise banner
your chickpeas into whole hummus
how about eliciting the nutritional and
antioxidant potential lentil sprouts
with
temperature stress instead
for example
what if you took your sprouts when they
were two days old and put them in the
fridge for an hour then you take them
out and let them continue to germinate
normally would that one hour of cold
stress make them more nutritious
or instead of putting them in the fridge
what if you lived in phoenix and took
them outside for an hour
here's what happens to a measure of the
antioxidant power of lentil sprouts
germinated the whole time at room
temperature a slow rise with time but
just that one hour in the fridge on day
two and days later significantly more
antioxidant buildup
same thing for an hour at 104 degrees
fahrenheit
what about then storing them in your
fridge sprouts are usually consumed
fresh however to keep them fresh we
usually stick them in the fridge but
there hasn't been any studies about the
effects of fridge stores on the
nutritional quality of sprouts
until
now
on days three through six you can see
the phenolic phytonutrient content of
sprouted peas decline but keep them in
the fridge and they go up instead
the same thing with mung bean sprouts
which are the typical bean sprouts
whereas in lentils
no significant difference
we should still keep them in the fridge
to prevent them from spoiling but the
best way to ensure maximum nutrition is
to sort them at
body temperature by
eating them
[Music]
this